# 叫蒜焖羊肉
This dish is called 'Stewed lamb with garlic'
# 不加任何香料
We are not adding any extra spices
# 就是大蒜和羊肉的结合
It's the simple combination of garlic and lamb
# 以前我就没觉得
I have never thought that
# 这羊肉跟大蒜结合这么好吃过
lamb tastes so good in combination with garlic
# 现在我是爱上它了
Now I've fallen in love with it
# 这羊肉一定要选一年以上的羊
We must choose lamb over 1 year old
# 羊肉选择是很讲究的
You need to be picky when choosing lamb for this dish
# 你要是羔羊不行 它没那口感 太嫩
Young lamb is not appropriate. It's too tender
# 羊肉选的部位是羊腩或者是前腿
You may choose lamb belly or front leg
# 一年以上的羊肉炖出来好吃 筋道
Lamb over 1-year-old is more delicious, providing a chewy texture
# 刀工还挺整齐 刀工一致 齐活
-Nice cutting skill. -Nicely cut, done!
# 吃之前一定要有一个浸泡的过程
You must soak the meat before cooking
# 之前我已经给它浸泡了几个小时了
I have soaked it for several hours in advance
# 然后咱们再给它清洗一下
Let's wash it now
# 把这血水给它拔出来
To completely remove the blood inside
# 然后今天咱这个菜
Our dish today
# 就是前期处理的时候很关键
relies heavily on the preparation step
# 因为肉是冻卷 是冻肉
Since we are using frozen lamb now
# 进过冷库的羊肉一定要
Frozen lamb must be
# 在处理的时候要仔细一点
carefully processed before cooking
# 其实为什么内蒙羊肉好吃
To be honest, why is the best lamb in Inner Mongolia?
# 一般人就是现宰现炖
That's because they cook the lamb directly after butchering
# 这个羊肉 您要是鲜肉就不用这么复杂
If you have fresh lamb, you don't really need to do all these
# 就直接上水 就直接给它煮就行了加盐
Simply boil it in water with some salt
# 但是这肉一冻完了之后
But once the meat is frozen
# 它腥膻味就加重
The taint strengthens
# 因为血水在里面闷着
because the blood remains in the meat (when frozen)
# 现在通过这么多年的实践
Based on our practice for so many years
# 一个羊肉一个鸡就不能冻 还有鸽子
It's better not to freeze lamb and chicken. And pigeon
# 只要一冻就完
They taste bad once frozen
# 大家看一眼 肉一定要冲到水清了
Please take a look. You must rinse the meat until the water becomes clear
# 然后这时候咱们凉水下锅了
Now let's boil it with cold water
# 肉要是不清的话
If you don't rinse the meat well
# 说句实话吃的味道就差远了
To be honest, it tastes much worse
# 鲜肉您没必要
However this does not apply to fresh meat
# 鲜肉您你怎么煮它都是清的
Fresh meat always tastes nice no matter how you deal with it #这句话有点意味不明...
# 这肉筋头筋脑的好吃
This cut tastes good because it contains tendon
# 我觉得我每回吃
Personally, I would always prefer
# 都愿意吃羊腩那块 或者前腿
Lamb belly or front leg
# 羊腩牛腩这都好吃
Lamb belly and beef brisket taste good
# 趁这机会我先把大蒜切了
Let me cut the garlic now
# 活不能闲着是吧
We should make full use of our time, right?
# 咱们蒜量一定要大 有半斤多
We must use a lot of garlic in this dish. More than 250 grams here
# 中间给它破开就行 一切两半
Simply cut it in the middle. Cut into two halves
# 第一这样好出味
Firstly, the flavor goes out easily
# 第二就是说
Secondly
# 这个蒜 它的个儿不能大过主料去
The size of the garlic should not exceed the main ingredient (lamb)
# 这道菜最早我吃的时候是在西北吃的
I had this dish for the first time in the northwest of China
# 然后回来之后
After I came back
# 结合咱们北京这块的口味
Based on the preference of flavor in Beijing
# 又重新给做了一个调整
I adjusted the recipe of this dish
# 这个汤出来是奶白色的
In my recipe, the soup is milky white
# 我们在当地吃的时候是清汤的
Back into the northwest, the broth was clear and transparent
# 都是鲜羊 咱们比不了
(In the northwest) they have fresh lamb, which we don't have here
# 然后这个羊肉用咱们冻卷一试
So I tried with frozen lamb to make this dish
# 做出奶白汤来了 我说这菜有意思
I was surprised that we could make milky white soup with frozen lamb
# 这也没有这么多香料
Here I am not using many spices
# 不能把羊肉的味给它盖了
Because we should avoid covering the original flavor of lamb
# 以前就是说这汤你可以留原汤
In previous dishes, you can use the original broth here (for further steps)
# 但是今天咱们这个不能用
But we cannot use this today
# 今天咱要用纯净水
We are using purified water instead
# 亮子 我有我自己的看法
Liangzi, I have my own idea on this issue
# 我估计大爷能赞同我的看法
I think Da Ye agrees with me
# 比如说我要做清汤的这种羊肉
For example, if I am going to make a lamb dish with clear broth
# 就是炖的汤也不要
I would rather discard the broth out of lamb
# 完全换成吊好的清鸡汤
I would use clear chicken broth
# 然后它合成的时候
When the chicken broth meets lamb
# 汤巨鲜 肉特别香
The soup becomes incredibly nice, and the meat tastes amazing
# 大爷他们做狮子头慢慢也发展了
Da Ye is also making some changes in his Shizitou (aka 'Lion Head') recipe
# 原来就是原汤 现在换成清鸡汤
In the old recipe, he used the original broth. Now it's changed into clear chicken broth
# 要不然搁点菌汤
Or mushroom broth
# 它也在随着人的需求在发展了
The recipe keeps developing according to customers' demands
# 咱们店里边卖清鸡汤羊蝎子
In our restaurant, the 'Lamb spine with clear chicken broth'
# 一直反响特别好
has always a been popular dish
# 行了 这开锅就行了
Okay. It's done when boiling
# 因为你这是冷水下锅
Because you are boiling from cold water
# 您看刚才这个肉看着
See? You may think the lamb looks very fatty
# 是不是觉得特别肥
before boiling
# 你看这回做完了之后这个肉
Now take another look. The lamb...
# 羊腩这块肥瘦相间 筋也多
The lamb belly is composed of lean meat and fat. Also some tendons
# 就适合炖的 烧的
It's very suitable for braising and brewing
# 汤底一定要用纯净水
You must use bottled water for the soup
# 对用好水 这个不能将就
Yes, you should use good water. Cannot compromise on that
# 或者净化过的水也行
or purified water
# 大爷这个羊肉我试过什么您知道么
Da Ye, let me tell you what I tried with lamb
# 那时候八几年 大爷
It was back into the 80s, Da Ye
# 就炖羊肉 就那老黄鸡扔进半只去
While brewing lamb, simply put half of an old chicken into the pot
# 那羊肉巨香 绝对的
The lamb was awesome. Absolutely
# 小亮你还得把老的传统弄出来
Xiao Liang, you need to preserve the old traditions
# 好啊 再结合一下
Sure. Combine the traditions with new situations
# 那绝对特别香那羊肉
The lamb is absolutely going to be incredibly tasty
# 不夸张的说你师父就是个神人
I am not flattering. Your master is a legend
# 敢想才能出好东西
You need to be brave enough to create good stuff
# 这个羊肉一定要洗它两遍到三遍
The lamb must be rinsed two or three times
# 因为这个步骤是很关键的一步
This is a really critical step
# 有一些网友啊
Some friends may think that
# 我们这儿羊肉没有你这么费事
'in my home, we don't have to do so much to prepare the lamb'
# 咱在家里边不比产地资源这么优势
Honestly, most people don't have nice lamb as you do in the place of production
# 一定要给它处理得干干净净
So we must wash it thoroughly
# 您店里边卖也是 您出来好吃才行
It's the same for restaurants. You must make sure it's delicious when the dish is done
# 这就行了
This should be ok.
# 水一开往里一搁就行
When the water is boiling, simply pouring it into this pot
# 这就齐了 都是原味
And that's done. All original flavor
# 这个辣椒放四个就行了
Let's put four dried chili peppers into the pot
# 一斤放肉一个 这是四斤肉
One chili pepper per 500 g of meat. We have 2 kg here
# 水开了 直接往里边一倒
The water is boiling. Directly pour into the pot
# 加什么调料么
Do we need to add any ingredient or spice?
# 什么都不加 连盐都不加
Nothing. Not even salt
# 酒呢 酒也不加
Wine? No wine
# 这汤多清亮啊
Look how clear the broth is
# 开火
Let's start heating
# 压了四十五分钟 又闷了二十五分钟
Pressure-cooked for 45 minutes. Then kept in the pot (sealed) for 25 minutes.
# 真烂乎 倍儿烫
That's totally stewed. Too hot
# 拿布拿布 我给你拿
Get a towel. Let me get one for you
# 其实他也烫 我还真不烫
-In fact he can feel the heat, too. -Not really!
# 咱们这个上面要是有油
If we have floating oil here
# 不要它 打掉它
Get rid of it with a spoon
# 下一步 先给它捞出来
Next step. Taking out of the water first
# （辣椒）不要了
Throw away (the chili peppers)
# 葱姜没有 就搁了四个辣椒
No ginger, no green onion. Just four chili peppers
# 原汁原味
That's the original flavor
# 进行下一步 煸蒜
Next step. Fry the garlic
# 半斤蒜 油不要太热 花生油
250 grams of garlic. The oil shouldn't be too hot. Use peanut oil
# 稍微让它有一起泡就行了 中火
Just let it bubble a bit. Use medium heat
# 千万不要油太热再下蒜
Never fry the garlic with overheated oil
# 要让它凉一点 别让它上色
Cook at a relatively low temperature. Don't let the garlic turn brown
# 表面一起泡 透了就行了
It's done when you can see small bubbles on the surface of garlic
# 这蒜出来应该是跟肉的颜色差不多
The garlic should have a similar color to the lamb (when the dish is done)
# 让它吃的得特别的面
The garlic will be very soft finally
# 这就行了 看见了吧
This is done. See that?
# 师父您照一下 全都起小泡了
Master, please shoot this. All with small bubbles
# 也不能让它上色 一上色这火就大了
Shouldn't let the garlic turn brown. In that case, the temperature is too high
# 把火加大
Now use high heat
# 这小锅翻的
Look how you toss the wok. Nice!
# 它有一个煸炒
We need a frying step here
# 这个原汤往里边加的时候
When you add the broth into the wok
# 一定要缓慢的往里加 烹进去
Make sure you do it slowly from the edge of the wok
# 一点一点往里加
Add the broth little by little
# 大火催开它 全都翻开了
Use high heat to boil the broth
# 就是边烧边加
Add broth while brewing
# 这一步是很关键的
This is a very critical step
# 师父您看这汤 奶白汤
-Master, look at the soup. -Milky white!
# 说句实话 当时我在
In fact, when I had this dish
# 人家西北那儿吃这个菜的时候
in the northwest
# 人家是清汤
That dish was served with clear broth
# 但是人家做的手法
But the receipe...
# 我都是按照人这手法做的
Basically I followed their recipe
# 这个汤一定要一点一点的加
You must add the broth slowly
# 实际上是在收汤 收汁
Actually this is also thickening the soup
# 正常情况下大火的话
Generally if we are using high heat (in the restaurant kitchen)
# 这汤比这还白还浓
The soup is more white and thick than we have here
# 他为什么逐步加汤
Why is he adding the broth in separate steps?
# 因为它这温度达不到
Because the temperature is not high enough here
# 你要一下闷了你就冲不出来了
If you add too much broth in one go, the fatty droplets stay inside the meat and will not go out #理论上奶白汤是由于脂肪滴的悬浊液，这里加了一点解释
# 您看刚才 大爷 我洗这么多遍
Look, Da Ye. I washed the meat so many times
# 目的就是为了要这个汤
Just because I want the white soup here
# 就要这汤 对 奶白汤
Just want the soup. -Yes, the milky white soup
# 再来一勺 诱人啊
One more spoon. That's intriguing
# 刚才咱们一点盐没有
We didn't add any salt just now
# 咱们调口的时候 这下就给它调够了
Now let's tune the flavor.
# 两勺盐 十克左右
Two spoons of salt. About 10 grams
# （白）胡椒粉的量一定要达到这样
(White) pepper powder. You must have this much
# 最关键的就是它了 胡椒粉
This is the most important ingredient
# 因为这个菜主要突出的就是
Because this dish relies on
# 它胡椒辣 就是胡椒的香味
the spicy flavor of pepper. The aroma of pepper
# 就盐和胡椒
Just salt and pepper
# 这个鲜度要比放味精还好 出锅
The umami flavor is even better than MSG. Ready to serve!
# 咱们这个菜是这么呈现的
That's how we present the dish
# 这叫“装羊蒜”
This is 'Zhuang yang suan' (homophonic to 'pretending to be dumb')
# 来 师父
Come on, master
# 这菜还真是
This dish is ...
# 别皱眉头
Don't frown
# 这个蒜吃着特别滑
The garlic is really smooth
# 而且到嘴里特别细腻
It gives a silky feeling in your mouth
# 大爷您知道 这有什么特点么
Da Ye, do you know what's special about this dish?
# 这菜做的是独树一帜
This dish is really unique
# 味道非常突出
With very outstanding flavor
# 大蒜和羊肉这个融合 挺好的
The combination between garlic and lamb
# 融合的好
Nice combination
# 其实我们做菜
Actually in terms of cooking
# 不管多少种调料 多少种烹调技法
No matter how many ingredients or cooking techniques we are using
# 最后的菜的境界 出来就是融合
The ultimate goal of a dish is combination
# 你这融合达到了高度
You are reaching a high level of combination
# 实际上我是不太爱吃炖羊肉的人
Actually I am not a big fan of stewed lamb
# 烤羊肉串 爆羊肉 涮羊肉都行
I prefer roasted lamb, stir-fried lamb, or hot pot with lamb slices
# 但是这种炖的
But stewed lamb...
# 不管是红烧清炖
No matter with a red thick sauce or clear broth
# 我实际上不太喜欢
I don't really enjoy those
# 但是今天 太喜欢了
-But today... -You love it much
# 用料简单 但是原料不简单
Simple ingredients, but not simple material #不太明白大爷当时想表达啥...
# 他调味调的太高了 你看什么都没有
He is really good at tuning the flavor. Look, almost nothing!
# 按二伯说的
According to Er Bai
# 调水也好 调情也好 调味也好
'Tune the water, tune the feel, tune the flavor' #这里可能也不太准确...
# 他调水调的好 他调水用的纯净水
He is really doing well in tuning the water. Using purified water
# 好的上等的前腿羊腩羊肉
Deceny lamb front leg, or belly
# 加上这么一大碗大蒜
And a big bowl of garlic
# 没有花椒 没有葱姜
No Sichuan peppercorns, no ginger and green onion
# 没有料酒 没有香辛料
No Chinese cooking wine, no other spices
# 就是两个原材料的融合
The simple combination of two materials
# 巧夺天工 彰显一章
Ingenious and unique
# 今儿我也看出来了
Today I can feel that
# 这么多年他跟着我
He's been following me for so many years
# 我们相识这么多年
We have known each other for so long
# 他尊重食材 这个了不起了
He respects the ingredients. That's already incredible
# 首先尊重师父 尊重食材
Firstly, you respect your master, and you respect the ingredients
# 尊重食材才能尊重别人呢
You must respect your ingredients before respecting others
# 你连食材都不尊重
How can you possibly make a nice dish
# 能做出好菜来么
if you do not respect the ingredients?
# 好 为小亮点赞
Good! Thumb up for Xiao Liang!
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you, Da Ye!